When did cholesterol actually become a
disease? High cholesterol is dangerous,
right? LDL, the bad cholesterol, clogs
your arteries. Lower cholesterol is
always better. Statins save lives. But
here's the question that a lot of people
don't ask about this. Is it actually
safe to have lower cholesterol? Does
that mean you're actually healthier?
Well, let's just take a look at it. Our
bodies make 3,000 milligrams of
cholesterol every single day. Why would
our bodies make that much cholesterol if
cholesterol was so damaging and
dangerous? In fact, if you don't eat
foods with cholesterol, your body makes
more. Babies are born with higher
cholesterol. Your brain is full of
cholesterol. I mean, let me ask you
this. Do you really think human beings
have evolved over 200,000 years making
something as a precursor that turns into
cell membranes, hormones, vitamin D,
bile salts, something that actually
repairs the body structurally makes up
the brain, helps support the immune
system. Our bodies use cholesterol in so
many different ways. Cholesterol is not
a poison. It's a building block. It's
essential in making the cell membranes.
Okay, without these membranes, you can't
have receptors for hormones to work.
Without cell membranes, you can't have
things go in and out of the cell
properly. Without these membranes, you
can't have the brain and nervous system
activate. Without these membranes, you
can't repair. And when a doctor measures
your cholesterol, they're looking at the
cholesterol in the blood. They're not
actually looking at cholesterol deep in
the cells where all the work is really
being done. So if you think about
cholesterol, cholesterol is kind of like
inside these little packages of these
protein delivery trucks. And the two
main types of cholesterol that people
focus on are HDL and the LDL. The HDL is
the delivery truck where we're taking
the cholesterol from the cells and
bringing it back to the liver to then
get recycled. And then the LDL is the
packaging or the truck that delivers
cholesterol to the cells. And people
associate LDL with the bad cholesterol.
But you have to realize there's two
types of LDL. You have the small dense
LDL particle size. And then you also
have the large buoyant, the bigger
particle size LDL. And unless you get an
advanced lipid profile test, they don't
really look at this right here. The
small dense LDL are the type that can go
in the cells and create inflammation and
problems. But that usually happens when
your glucose is high and you have
insulin problems and you have
inflammation and you're eating poorly.
When you're on a low carb diet and you
don't have insulin resistance, you're
going to have more large buoyant
LDL which is not going to invade the
inside of the arteries. So, this is why
it's so important to get an advanced
lipid profile test to look at the ratios
of how many of this versus this right
here because if you have high LDL, but
it's of this type, this particle size,
this is not pathogenic, okay? So, you
don't have to worry about it. When
someone does have high cholesterol in
general, you have to really think about
why that could be. Number one, you could
be going through stress because part of
the raw material or the building blocks
or the precursors for cortisol hormone,
which is a stress hormone, is
cholesterol. And you just might need
more raw material to make more of those
hormones to cope with the stress. Also,
testosterone is made from cholesterol.
So, when someone gets on an anti-
cholesterol drug to block the production
of cholesterol, they're going to have a
lot of problems with their muscles
because they're going to block the
formation of testosterone, which
actually is needed for your muscles. But
not only that, statin also blocks
something called co-enzyme Q10. I talk
about that in another video. I'll put
that link down below. But when you have
low cholesterol, you're not going to be
able to make as much bile. So, you can't
really get the full absorption of fats.
You're not going to have enough raw
material to make vitamin D. Think about
this. Sun hits your skin, it turns the
cholesterol in your skin to vitamin D.
If you don't have enough cholesterol,
you can't make enough vitamin D. Vitamin
D is one of the most important vitamins
that you can possibly have. There are
just as many, if not more, problems with
low cholesterol as there are with high
cholesterol. But that's an area that we
really don't talk about. In fact, I've
never heard this before of a doctor
saying, "Oh, your cholesterol is too
low. We have to increase it." In
reality, high cholesterol is not a
disease. Your body makes cholesterol. If
your cholesterol is high, it's important
to understand why it's high. But that
just explains what's happening way
downstream of the consequence of
something else over here. I don't know
if you knew this, but if you eat a lot
of refined sugar and starches, your
cholesterol will go up from that because
that starch will convert into
cholesterol. That could be one reason
that's a root cause. Your triglycerides
are going to go up if your dietary
sugars and starches are high as well. If
you have more inflammation, the need for
cholesterol goes way up as well. If your
body needs more repair, your cholesterol
will go up. This is simple biochemistry
and it's so important not to think
cholesterol is a disease. It's something
our body makes. It's a necessary
precursor and you really need to know
the whole picture. Millions and millions
of people are on statins right now
because they're afraid that the high
cholesterol is going to damage their
hearts. If high cholesterol is actually
killing people, then older adults with
higher cholesterol would be dying first.
But you don't see that. Some of the
oldest people alive have high
cholesterol. There is no association
between people with high cholesterol and
higher rates of dying. Low cholesterol
in older adults is linked to higher
rates of death from all causes. So low
cholesterol does not equal safe. It
doesn't equal longevity. Lower
cholesterol is linked to lowered
immunity,
depression, memory problems, hormone
problems. Remember, your brain is mostly
fat. You starve it of cholesterol and
it's going to suffer. In nature,
cholesterol goes up in the winter. One
reason could be because you need to make
more vitamin D, but then the summer
comes, it goes down. Why? One theory of
that is because that sunlight is turning
your cholesterol into vitamin D. And so
if that's true, if you're out of the sun
and you're living indoors all the time,
cholesterol is going to build up because
you get no conversion into these other
things like vitamin D. So it's kind of
like a permanent winter all the time. So
we keep asking the wrong question. How
can we keep pushing cholesterol lower
and lower and lower? But we never ask
the real question. Is it safe to live
with low cholesterol? Cholesterol is not
the enemy. It's something that our
bodies create because our bodies have
been making cholesterol for a very long
time. It's not the enemy. It's not a
disease. In fact, it's a protection
against a lot of problems.